<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>50 Lines of Code</title>
    <link>https://50linesofco.de/</link>
    <description>The /var/log of Martin Naumann</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <pubDate>Fri, 11 May 2018 17:50:11 GMT</pubDate>
    <item>
	<title>Writing an x86 "Hello world" bootloader with assembly</title>
	<link>https://50linesofco.de/post/2018-02-28-writing-an-x86-hello-world-bootloader-with-assembly.html</link>
	<description>After booting, the BIOS of the computer reads 512 bytes from the boot devices and, if it detects a two-byte "magic number" at the end of those 512 bytes, loads the data from these 512 bytes as code and runs it. 

This kind of code is called a "bootloader" (or "boot sector") and we're writing a tiny bit of assembly code to make a virtual machine run our code and display "Hello world" for the fun of it. Bootloaders are also the very first stage of booting an operating system.
</description>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://50linesofco.de/post/2018-02-28-writing-an-x86-hello-world-bootloader-with-assembly.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
	<title>Firefox day 5: A race</title>
	<link>https://50linesofco.de/post/2017-06-18-firefox-day-5-a-race.html</link>
	<description>I've opened a session with four tabs:

1. Facebook
2. Twitter
3. A Stackoverflow thread
4. A Github page
5. An Archilogic model with a 3D model

I measured the total memory usage, then left them open for a 30 minutes and measured the memory usage afterwards.
Then I did the same with Firefox.

Chrome started with 420 MB when all pages where opened on Linux and consumed  520 MB after half an hour.
Firefox started with 575 MB when all pages where opened on Linux and consumed 960 MB after half an hour.

![](../images/post-images/firefox/firefox-day5-1.png)

I don't know about the marketing graphic Firefox has distributed, but it doesn't reflect what I'm seeing on my Linux laptop, unless my method is wrong:

1. Launch the websites
2. Read the RSS for all browser processes

Also: Your milage may vary, I guess.</description>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://50linesofco.de/post/2017-06-18-firefox-day-5-a-race.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
	<title>Firefox day 4: Goin' up the country</title>
	<link>https://50linesofco.de/post/2017-06-17-firefox-day-4-goin-up-the-country.html</link>
	<description>I've found a few niceties besides the fact that **apps open links with Firefox in the background and with a little button you can tap to switch** directly to the browser - let's look at those!



For instance Firefox **detects if you already have an open tab with the URL** you're typing in. It then offers the possibility to jump tho that tab immediately:



It also indicates if the **URL can be opened in an installed app** on the phone:



The little Android icon in the address bar can be tapped and opens the URL in the app - in this case in YouTube.

Also, tabs that are opened via an app and **wait in the background show up in the notifications**, which allows for a quite nice way of accessing them later on:

</description>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://50linesofco.de/post/2017-06-17-firefox-day-4-goin-up-the-country.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
	<title>Firefox day 3: Details</title>
	<link>https://50linesofco.de/post/2017-06-16-firefox-day-3-details.html</link>
	<description>When switching browsers three days ago, I forgot to install an ad blocker.
I have to say I'm surprised **how well Firefox seems to deal with ads** as I haven't really noticed any ads up to this point.



However, the day had to come where an ad banner popped into a website, prompting me to install [uBlock origin](https://addons.mozilla.org/en/firefox/addon/ublock-origin/?src=hp-dl-featured).</description>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://50linesofco.de/post/2017-06-16-firefox-day-3-details.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
	<title>Firefox day 2: First few cracks</title>
	<link>https://50linesofco.de/post/2017-06-15-firefox-day-2-first-few-cracks.html</link>
	<description>Today I happened to visit my own website, [geekonaut.de](http://geekonaut.de) and noticed a few interesting glitches on my page:

![](../images/post-images/firefox/firefox-day2-4.png)

The first thing to do was to go to the devtools and inspect the elements:
![](../images/post-images/firefox/firefox-day2-3.png)

So the 3D transforms aren't doing too well on my trusty linux laptop. I've not seen this problem with Chrome. Then again, graphics can be wonky on Linux, so I double checked with my OSX machine to find that it's indeed a **compatibility bug between Firefox and Linux** in my case.

Also for some reason Firefox required me to put an `overflow-x: hidden` into an element that is styled to be `width: 100vh` and displayed as such. No biggie but something I'll investigate further as I can't fully explain it yet.</description>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://50linesofco.de/post/2017-06-15-firefox-day-2-first-few-cracks.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
	<title>My Firefox month: Day 1</title>
	<link>https://50linesofco.de/post/2017-06-14-my-firefox-month-day-1.html</link>
	<description>* I will try Firefox 54 on my laptops and phone for a month
* Firefox Sync provides me with seamless access to my tabs, bookmarks, autofill data etc. across devices
* Using Firefox with multiple profiles is easier with an Add-On like "Profile Switcher"
* The first day had a bunch of pleasant surprises in the dev tools</description>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://50linesofco.de/post/2017-06-14-my-firefox-month-day-1.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
	<title>How I approach side projects</title>
	<link>https://50linesofco.de/post/2017-05-08-how-i-approach-side-projects.html</link>
	<description>- Start with something you don't know. Research &amp; write down the result
- Research just enough to identify the major unknown-unknowns, turning them into known-unknowns
- Break your project down into approachable steps
- Build small prototypes for each step to validate your understanding of the project's problem
- Put together an implementation of your project, based on learnings from the prototypes
- 🎈 Be proud &amp; share 🎈</description>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://50linesofco.de/post/2017-05-08-how-i-approach-side-projects.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
	<title>CORS - a guided tour</title>
	<link>https://50linesofco.de/post/2017-03-06-cors-a-guided-tour.html</link>
	<description>* The browser enforces the [Same-origin policy](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Same-origin_policy) to avoid getting responses from websites that do not share the same origin.
* The Same-origin policy does not prevent requests being made to other origins, but disables access to the response from JavaScript.
* [CORS](https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTTP/Access_control_CORS) headers allow access to cross-origin responses.
* CORS together with credentials require caution.
* CORS is a browser-enforced policy. Other applications aren't affected by it.</description>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://50linesofco.de/post/2017-03-06-cors-a-guided-tour.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
	<title>Bits and bytes in JavaScript</title>
	<link>https://50linesofco.de/post/2017-02-13-bits-and-bytes-in-javascript.html</link>
	<description>* when dealing with binary data or communicating with hardware, you may find yourself needing ways to manipulate individual bits
* JavaScript has operations for this case:
** bit-shift operators push bits to the left or right
** bit-wise arithmetic operators merge two sets of bits or flip the bits
* when dealing with bytes, ArrayBuffers allow different ways of handling the data without needing to copy it around</description>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://50linesofco.de/post/2017-02-13-bits-and-bytes-in-javascript.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
	<title>JavaScript in parallel</title>
	<link>https://50linesofco.de/post/2017-02-06-javascript-in-parallel-web-workers-transferables-and-sharedarraybuffer.html</link>
	<description>* JavaScript is single-threaded and long-running scripts make the page unresponsive
* Web Workers allow running JavaScript in separate threads, communicating with the main thread using messages.
* Messages that transfer large amount of data in TypedArrays or ArrayBuffers cause large memory cost due to data being cloned
* Using transfers mitigates the memory cost of cloning, but makes the data inaccessible to the sender
* SharedArrayBuffers are an upcoming feature, allowing data to be shared between threads.
* SharedArrayBuffer access can (and may need to) be synced using Atomics
* All code can be found [in this repository](https://github.com/AVGP/js-parallelism-demos)</description>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://50linesofco.de/post/2017-02-06-javascript-in-parallel-web-workers-transferables-and-sharedarraybuffer.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
	<title>Understanding different number systems</title>
	<link>https://50linesofco.de/post/2017-01-16-understanding-different-number-systems.html</link>
	<description>![Leibnitz' notes on the binary system](../images/post-images/binary-system.jpg)

* The fact that we use a number system with 10 symbols (0-9),aka "Base 10" or decimal is an arbitrary choice
* Systems with different bases can help us express numbers in specific contexts more intuitively (e.g. hexadecimal or binary when working with digital systems)
* Reading numbers in any number system can be done by multiplying each digit value with a power of the base, starting with the zero-th power for the right most digit and increasing the exponent by one for each step to the left, e.g. 123 = `3x10^0 + 2x10^1 + 1x10^2` for decimal numbers (base 10)</description>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://50linesofco.de/post/2017-01-16-understanding-different-number-systems.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
	<title>2016: The year in review</title>
	<link>https://50linesofco.de/post/2016-12-21-2016-the-year-in-review.html</link>
	<description>

This year I finally finished the draft of my book on Polymer!
If things work out, it will be in print at the beginning of next year... which makes me very happy.
Right after finishing the raw script in May (a mere week before my wedding) I swore I'd never write a book again but I was very happy to have pushed through. Fun fact: I am writing another book now, so there's that.

I also had the honour to give an [interview about WebVR](https://habrahabr.ru/company/jugru/blog/315868/) to the russian Java User Group. It's in Russian, but Google Translate seems to be keeping up with it quite well.

Right now I have a few more writing projects brewing, both for books and articles, so watch this space if you're interested in me sharing more of the things I failed at and what I learned while doing so.

In addition, I am happy to announce that I am now also a [Google Developer Expert]() for Web. This means that Google will support me in mentoring and helping developers and creating content to share my knowledge with the broader web developer community.

</description>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://50linesofco.de/post/2016-12-21-2016-the-year-in-review.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
	<title>HTML, DOM and JavaScript unraveled</title>
	<link>https://50linesofco.de/post/2016-10-16-html-dom-and-javascript-unraveled.html</link>
	<description>The web platform has started out with HTML to allow users to share documents
and link them in a user friendly and standardised way.

HTML alone was lacking the possibility to influence the way things looked, so
a new standard came about ([after other alternatives have been proposed](https://eager.io/blog/the-languages-which-almost-were-css/)), CSS.

Around the same time (depending on what you consider the beginning of CSS's existence)
[JavaScript was created by Brendan Eich](https://www.w3.org/community/webed/wiki/A_Short_History_of_JavaScript)
and a few years later a way to interact with the HTML document from JavaScript was created, the [DOM](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Document_Object_Model).

Today, the different technologies may be a little too much to take in at first
and it won't get easier as things such as the Shadow DOM is added and frameworks and libraries may bring a Virtual DOM along.

So let's dive right in an have a look at the different bits and pieces that are at play here.</description>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://50linesofco.de/post/2016-10-16-html-dom-and-javascript-unraveled.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
	<title>The overwhelming web</title>
	<link>https://50linesofco.de/post/2016-07-04-the-overwhelming-web.html</link>
	<description>Web Development can be pretty strange these days.

On the one hand we tell beginners that they need ALL the things:
build tools, task runners, package managers, frameworks, polyfills, libraries, runtimes and
deployment systems.

On the other hand some are airing their concerns about some flavour of "fatigue",
be it a framework, library, JavaScript or even frontend fatigue.

I also noticed a sense of urgency for *everything*. Mobile-first, Offline-first, Accessibility-first, Content-first and the list goes on. It starts to feel like "everything-first", which of course really would mean: Nothing first.

Where are the olden days, where all you needed to build websites was a text editor and some space online to put it?</description>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://50linesofco.de/post/2016-07-04-the-overwhelming-web.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
	<title>Slick and slf4j MDC logging in Scala</title>
	<link>https://50linesofco.de/post/2016-07-01-slick-and-slf4j-mdc-logging-in-scala.html</link>
	<description>* Multi-user applications need log messages to retain **context**, so the situation can be examined on a transaction-basis
* The **mapped diagnostic context**, short `MDC`, allows to put context to all log statements for a single thread
* Scala allows us to build an `ExecutionContext` where we can copy the `MDC` to any new thread that is being used giving us **multi-thread MDC logging**
* Slick requires us to also provide an `Executor` that uses this `ExecutionContext`
* There's a package for that: `de.geekonaut.slickmdc`</description>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://50linesofco.de/post/2016-07-01-slick-and-slf4j-mdc-logging-in-scala.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
	<title>Five rules to stay sane and efficient when handling downtimes</title>
	<link>https://50linesofco.de/post/2016-03-17-five-rules-to-stay-sane-and-efficient-when-handling-downtimes.html</link>
	<description>Downtimes, Crashes, Incidents, System Failures - they have many names, but most people involved with technology to some degree have experienced at least one at some point in their career.

I've seen many different teams and many different incarnations of the above-mentioned situations. I've been on the different sides of them: The user, the developer, the system administrator, the site reliability engineer and the consultant.

Some of them I have caused, some of them I helped to resolve and in some of them I was a mere bystander.

This post is the distilled essence on how different teams that I had the pleasure of being a member, dealt and deal with the stress and the specific characteristics of these tense situations to ensure timely and proper resolution.</description>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://50linesofco.de/post/2016-03-17-five-rules-to-stay-sane-and-efficient-when-handling-downtimes.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
	<title>Five rules to stay levelheaded and efficient when handling downtimes</title>
	<link>https://50linesofco.de/post/2016-03-17-five-rules-to-stay-levelheaded-and-efficient-when-handling-downtimes.html</link>
	<description>Downtimes, Crashes, Incidents, System Failures - they have many names, but most people involved with technology to some degree have experienced at least one at some point in their career.

I've seen many different teams and many different incarnations of the above-mentioned situations. I've been on the different sides of them: The user, the developer, the system administrator, the site reliability engineer and the consultant.

Some of them I have caused, some of them I helped to resolve and in some of them I was a mere bystander.

This post is the distilled essence on how different teams that I had the pleasure of being a member, dealt and deal with the stress and the specific characteristics of these tense situations to ensure timely and proper resolution.</description>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://50linesofco.de/post/2016-03-17-five-rules-to-stay-levelheaded-and-efficient-when-handling-downtimes.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
	<title>JSON RPC 2.0 - for simple and powerful APIs</title>
	<link>https://50linesofco.de/post/2016-03-09-json-rpc-2-for-simple-and-powerful-apis.html</link>
	<description>To my surprise a contender in the field of API protocols is yet unknown: JSON-RPC 2.0.
A standard since 2010, it is simple yet powerful but barely known amongst developers.
This article explains what it is, what makes it different and nice to work with and how to use it.</description>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://50linesofco.de/post/2016-03-09-json-rpc-2-for-simple-and-powerful-apis.html</guid>
</item>
  </channel>
</rss>
